Guide to the Guion Family Papers circa 1870-1930, 1968 MS 3013
New-York Historical Society
Guion family papers
Circa 1870-1930, 1968
1900-1929
New-York Historical Society
Guion family
MS 3013
3.15 Linear feet in 8 document boxes and 1 oversize folder
This collection contains correspondence to and from members of the Guion family between 1870 and 1930. The primary correspondent, Martha Guion, lived in New York City. Also included are legal documents, newspaper clippings, calling cards, photographs, cabinet cards, stereographs, and other materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the descendants of the Guion Family post-1968.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged into the following three series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Legal Papers, Ephemera, and Other Materials
Series III: Photographs
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Materials at New York Historical Society
The diary of Mary Guion Brown (1782-1871) is housed in the Manuscripts Department of the New-York Historical Society with the call number BV Guion, Mary
Scope and Contents Note
This collection is comprised of predominantly personal correspondence of the Guion family from approximately 1870-1930.
Seres I. Correspondence: The main correspondent is Martha Guion of New York City. Other correspondents include Frances Guion, Antoinette Guion Nugent, Horace Nugent, and Granville Nugent, among other members of the extended Guion family, as well as friends and acquaintances. The letters mainly discuss family matters and relationships, finances, legal issues, travel, and world news.
Series II. Legal Papers, Ephemera and Other Materials: Includes legal documents relating to deeds, mortgages, and trusts; newspaper clippings; calling cards from friends and neighbors; academic report cards; programs from different entertainment activities; account ledgers for groceries, seafood, and butchers meat; as well as diaries, of which the bound diary includes recipes towards the end.
Series III. Photographs: Includes a selection of photographs, stereographs, cabinet cards, and a few negatives. The photographs are both posed and candid images of the extended Guion family, as well as a large selection of photographs of animals, which George Guion used as reference for painting. There are two photograph albums: One is of an unmarked wedding from the 1920's, and the second includes prints of animals sent to George. While most of the photographs are completely unmarked, some are labeled with the individuals who are in the image or the date, and a few have notes on the back.
Biographical Note
Names in bold designate individuals included within the collection.
Clement Guion (1814-1883) married Elizabeth Jane Gibson in 1838. Seven of their ten children are represented in the collection.
1) George Gibson Guion (1841-1912) married Imogene Louise Hart in 1865. They had six children, three of whom died in infancy. Of the surviving children, Clement (1866-1917) married Julia Banks, Hobart (1868-1950) married Harriet McAllister, and George (1870-1864) married Amelia McAllister. George Gibson Guion was a Lieutenant in the 7th New York Militia in the Union Army during the American Civil War. His sons, George and Clement, moved to Litchfield, Connecticut, worked together in real estate and insurance, and George painted.
2) Mary Louise Guion Thompson (1843-1873) married William W. Thompson.
3) Anna Guion Howard married Frederick William Howard in 1874
4) Clementine Guion Young (1845-?) married Ebenezer Young in 1870.
5) Frances Guion (1855-?) never married. She was committed to the Middletown State Homeopathic Hospital for insanity in 1922. She was also known as 'Fan" to her family.
6) Martha Guion (1856-?) never married. She was also known as "Martie", "Marty", and "Aunta" to her family. Her nephew, Granville, considered her his foster mother.
7) Antoinette Guion Nugent (1862-?) married Horace (Horry) Nugent in 1863, and had a son Granville (Grannie). Horace was a Senior British Vice-Counsul, and was stationed in Galveston, TX as Counsul to Texas and New Mexico. Granville split his time between the United States and the United Kingdom, and therefore attended school in both countries. Antoinette was also known as "Net" and "Nettie" to her family.
Wood Gibson Sr. and Wood Gibson Jr. were the father and brother of Elizabeth Jane Gibson.
Guion family
- Series I: Correspondence, 1875-1929
  - Correspondence, 1875-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (Martha), 1884-1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1894-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Dear Mrs. Guion), 1902-1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1919 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (From Grannie to Martha), 1914-1928 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1919 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Martha to Net), 1916-1917 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1921 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (To Martha), 1918-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Net and Martha), 1920, 1925-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1923 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Dear Martha Guion), 1920-1924 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1924 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1926 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1924 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1929 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Granville), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Granville), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Granville), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Martha Guion), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (incomplete), Undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (incomplete), Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (incomplete), Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
- Series II: Legal Papers, Ephemera, and Other Materials, 1870-1930
  - Incomplete letters, photos, newspaper clippings, etc, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Incomplete letters, cards, etc., Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Miscellaneous, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Incomplete letters, photos, cards, etc., Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: Newspaper clippings, wedding invitations, calling cards, etc., Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Unbound Diary, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Legal papers: Wood Gibson, Undated, 1900, 1902, 1909 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Legal Papers: Estate of Wood Gibson, 1900 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legal Papers: Wood Gibson, 1900 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Legal Papers: Elizabeth Guion, 1889, 1890, 1912 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Legal Papers: Frances Guion and Martha Guion, 1899-1929 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legal papers: Miscellaneous, 1870-1922 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Various ledgers, account books, and journals, Undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Romance in Family History", 1968 (Offsite-box 8, Volume BV Guion Papers 1)
  - Poster. Advertisement for Executor's Sale for Estate of Elizabeth J. Guion. Oversize, 1898 (Box-folder OS-Medium)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Identifies the locations of properties in New York City and elsewhere to be sold.
  - Certificate. Oversize, 1892 (Box-folder OS-Medium)
    Includes a portion of the certificate from U.S. President Benjamin Harrison recognizing the appointment of Horace Dickinson Nugent as Consul from Britain for Texas and the territory of New Mexico. Much of the lower portion of the certificate is missing, including the seal and signature.
- Series III: Photographs
  - Unidentified Photographs, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified Photographs, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Animals, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 3)
  - Guion Photos: George?: For Painting?, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4)
  - Louise Shelton et al?, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 5)
  - Hobart, George, Etc., Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6)
  - George Guion: Artist, Undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 7)
  - Unmarked Wedding Album, circa 1920 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photo Album, Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mixed Photographs, Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - Imogene Hart et al., Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3)
  - Framed Photograph with notes on back, Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photographs. Oversize, Undated (Box-folder OS-Medium)
    Includes Francis Marion McAllister, Benjamin Clark Cutler, a house in New Rochelle, and unidentified children.